<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Neuropsychology | Reality Bending League</title>
    <link>/tag/neuropsychology/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/neuropsychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Neuropsychology</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Reality Bending League</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu2cedcd67292931a8a21afc6006ffd93f_49000_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Neuropsychology</title>
      <link>/tag/neuropsychology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>What visual agnosia might feel like</title>
      <link>/post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;name-one-thing-in-this-photo&#34;&gt;Name One Thing In This Photo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you name &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; thing in the image above?&lt;/strong&gt; It all looks familiar, but something is off. The image makes &amp;ldquo;sense&amp;rdquo; overall; there are well-defined shapes and objects, that seem to be placed in a plausible - albeit chaotic - fashion, like some random rubbish thrown in the corner of a room. Even the colors, the lightning, the quality, is coherent, and helps making it believable. And yet, chances are you cannot name one single element that composes it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This image, after appearing on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/melip0ne/status/1120503955526750208?s=20&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; in April 2019, surfaced on reddit with the caption &amp;ldquo;This picture is &lt;strong&gt;designed to give the viewer the simulated experience of having a stroke&lt;/strong&gt; (particularly in the &lt;strong&gt;occipital lobe&lt;/strong&gt; of the cerebral cortex, where visual perception occurs.) &lt;strong&gt;Everything looks hauntingly familiar but you just can&amp;rsquo;t quite recognize anything&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;, and became subsequently &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-6959547/Extremely-frustrating-slightly-disturbing-image-goes-viral.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;viral&lt;/a&gt;. However, the author of the caption later admitted that he made this description up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So where does the image come from?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can trace back the original publication to an &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/0F7XBwFwA-M?t=104&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;instagram account&lt;/a&gt;, which author declared having made the image using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.artbreeder.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ArtBreeder.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This website gives access to an AI algorithm (Generative Adversarial Networks - GAN), commonly used in the processing and generation of images (one mindblowing example can be found on &lt;a href=&#34;https://thispersondoesnotexist.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;thispersondoesnotexist.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which generates realistic pictures of non-existing people). There were even some attempts to &lt;em&gt;reverse engineer&lt;/em&gt; the process to retrieve what the original image could have been like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.kym-cdn.com/photos/images/original/001/486/325/1dd.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, it seems like there is no intelligent design behind this image. No clever neuropsychologist carefully crafting a meaningful experience. Just one of these lucky accident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, it&amp;rsquo;s still an intriguing image, falling in this uncanny abyss of things that we recognize as familiar, but slightly too alien for our sense-seeking brains to dissolve in meaning. &lt;strong&gt;Could it tell something about brain processes?&lt;/strong&gt; Surely, but &lt;strong&gt;brain disorders?&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;occipital stroke&amp;rdquo; hypothesis&lt;/strong&gt; mentioned above suggests, by its formulation, a lesion to the primary visual cortices. However, as neuroscientists know, these brain regions, located at the extreme back of the brain, are mostly supporting lower level aspects of visual processing, and their damage is usually related to alterations of a somewhat different nature than of that above, such as vision loss, visual hallucinations, visual deformations, loss of color, movement, stereoscopy, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is another neuropsychological disorder, referred to as &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;visual agnosia&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, in which patients experience difficulties to recognize visually presented objects, despite preserving an intact vision. In fact, it is more an umbrella term for different subcategories of deficits, and the image above could be reminiscent of visual agnosia of the &lt;em&gt;associative&lt;/em&gt; type, which corresponds to a a specific impairment in the assignment of meaning to a stimulus that is accurately perceived (and can be visually described). This symptom is often related to injuries in the left occipito-temporal region, located on the ventral &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rdquo; stream of the brain (as opposed to the so-called &amp;ldquo;where&amp;rdquo; dorsal stream).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;whatstream.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ivan-seals-art&#34;&gt;Ivan Seal&amp;rsquo;s Art&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, the youtuber &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCR6LasBpceuYUhuLToKBzvQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Solar Sands&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; helped me discover the artist &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Seal&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ivan Seal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which work is somewhat akin to the image above. They are not purely abstract renditions, or depictions of impossible entities, but plausible objects that sit in this awkward space, deep between boring reality and total weirdness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://rca-media.rca.ac.uk/images/dumtrimiestonmo_blurosperiod150x100_cm_-_Phot.width-1000.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.redd.it/ywee14vpk8y41.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to tweet and share this post and don&amp;rsquo;t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; 🐦 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is Reality Bending?</title>
      <link>/post/2020-09-28-what_is_realitybending/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/2020-09-28-what_is_realitybending/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As you know, &lt;strong&gt;reality bending&lt;/strong&gt; is my primary research direction. However, it is not (yet) a well-established scientific topic, nor is it clearly defined. In fact, &lt;strong&gt;it is not defined at all, hence the purpose of this article&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what does it refer too? Is it some kind of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avatar:_The_Last_Airbender&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avatar: The Last Airbender&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; thing? Or some &lt;a href=&#34;https://marvel-movies.fandom.com/wiki/Reality_Stone&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avengers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-style superpower? Well&amp;hellip; I sure wish it was 😁&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, &lt;strong&gt;reality bending&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the study of the internal and external determinants of subjective reality. In other words, we seek to understand the processes that modulate our conscious experience of reality. The word &amp;ldquo;bending&amp;rdquo; encapsulates the active nature of the mechanisms at stake. Indeed, being anything but stable, our perception of reality can be quite easily influenced, whether voluntarily or not, sometimes to extreme degrees of alteration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;DonQuixote.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;github for psychologists&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Daumier, H. (1925), Don Quixote attacking the windmills.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reality benders&lt;/strong&gt; seek to unravel the structure and mechanisms of the sense of reality by studying natural instances of its distortion, or by directly inducing them through a variety of means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective-and-subjective-determinants-of-the-sense-of-reality&#34;&gt;Objective and subjective determinants of the sense of reality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take for example a guy watching some episode of his favourite TV show, &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt;. As he swiftly moves from laughing to snivelling, we can confidently say that he is fully &lt;strong&gt;immersed&lt;/strong&gt; in the show. He feels like he&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;present&lt;/em&gt; in the show, from which the fictional characters &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; very real: for a moment, his brain processes the perceived experience almost as if it was real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What leads to this high sense of reality? First, there are &lt;strong&gt;objective characteristics&lt;/strong&gt; of the experience (or rather, of the external source of the experience), i.e., characteristics of the environment. Here, it&amp;rsquo;s a realistic stimulus displayed on a flat screen. But one could wonder what would happen if the sensory input was richer (imagine being physically IN the show by means of some super &lt;strong&gt;virtual reality&lt;/strong&gt; setup), or poorer (the same story presented as comic strips with the characters portrayed as stick figures).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while such manipulations could indeed be used to manipulate our immersion, there is also a &lt;strong&gt;subjective component&lt;/strong&gt; contributing to our sense of reality, related for instance to the affective response, attentional engagement, or self-relevance, that will cause a stimulus to strum unique strings in each individual, depending on his history and state of mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tell-me-your-reality-and-ill-tell-you-who-you-are&#34;&gt;Tell me your reality and I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you who you are&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that the sense of reality is, in the end, a subjective experience, means that is is intrinsically connected to the Self (i.e., our physical and mental identity). As such, aside from studying how our sense of reality is influenced by external and internal factors, but also investigate the reverse relationship, i.e., &lt;strong&gt;how the variability of our sense of reality can inform us about oneself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that, although the focus is the subjective aspect of reality, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that we deny the existence, or downplay the importance, of objective reality. Stating that most of our experience is &amp;ldquo;made-up&amp;rdquo; (i.e., is a construction of the brain) does not equate absolute relativism (more on that in another post). Objective truths and facts do exist, and are essential to seek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;altered-states-of-consciousness&#34;&gt;Altered states of consciousness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, states in which our sense of reality is distorted (as compared to the consensual collective experience) are of particular interest as models or study-cases of our ideas and theories. They include long-term affections (e.g., neuropsychiatric disorders such as schizophrenia) or transcient states (induced by psychoactive substances or specific practices like meditation and trance).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to tweet and share this post, and leave a comment below&lt;/em&gt; 🤗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🐦 &lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
